Guide to the Tom Rankin photographs, 1980-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Tom Rankin photographs 1980-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rankin, Tom.
9.0 linear feet Extent: 106 Items
Tom Rankin is a documentary photographer, filmmaker, folklorist, professor of art and documentary studies, and former director of the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University. The Tom Rankin photographs collection dates from 1980-2008 and consists of black and white and color large-format and contact prints from Rankin's work documenting the American South, particularly religious sites, rituals, and communities in the Mississippi Delta region. A selection of Rankin's photographs was published in Sacred Space: Photographs from the Mississippi Delta, 1993. Other prints portray various places and people elsewhere in the American South; another series features as its subject Mississippi writer Larry Brown. There is also a digital audio recording of a talk by Rankin at the exhibit opening of his work, Near the Cross: Photographs from the Mississippi Delta. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
rankintom
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. However, publication and commercial use requires the permission of the photographer.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Tom Rankin Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 2007-2008.
Biographical Note
Tom Rankin served as the Director of the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University for three consecutive five-year terms until 2013, and is a Professor of the Practice in the Arts at Duke University. A documentary photographer, filmmaker, writer, editor, and folklorist, he has been documenting and interpreting American culture, particularly in the South, for nearly twenty years. His photographic work has been published and widely exhibited. His most long-standing work has been to reveal through the documentary arts the culture and society of the Mississippi Delta region, where he has also served as a faculty member of Delta State University and the University of Mississippi. He has returned many times since the 1980s to photograph the landscapes and people of the Mississippi Delta, most recently in 2011 after the great floods of that year. His books include Sacred Space: Photographs from the Mississippi Delta (1993), which received the Mississippi Institute of Arts and Letters Award for Photography, 'Deaf Maggie Lee Sayre': Photographs of a River Life(1995), Faulkner's World: The Photographs of Martin J. Dain (1997), and Local Heroes Changing America: Indivisible (2000). He received an MFA from Georgia State University and an MA from the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. American Photo Magazine named Tom Rankin as one of the 100 Most Important People in Photography, May, 2005.
Collection Overview
The Tom Rankin photographs collection dates from 1980-2008 and consists of black and white and color prints from Rankin's work documenting the American South, particularly religious sites, rituals, and communities in the Mississippi Delta region. A selection of Rankin's photographs was published in Sacred Space: Photographs from the Mississippi Delta, 1993. Other prints portray various places and people elsewhere in the American South; another series features as its subject Mississippi writer Larry Brown. In addition to the large-format black and white gelatin silver and color photographic prints, some of which are matted, there are also smaller contact prints. There is also a digital audio recording in mp3 format of a talk by Rankin at the exhibit opening of his work, Near the Cross: Photographs from the Mississippi Delta. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Collection Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by project: Larry Brown; Mississippi Delta; Portraits of the American South; and Sacred Space. Within those bodies of work, prints are in order as received from the photographer.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Rankin, Tom; Brown, Larry, 1951-2004; Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies; African Americans -- Mississippi; Documentary photographers -- North Carolina; Documentary photography -- United States; Mississippi -- Pictorial works; Mississippi -- Religious life; Mississippi -- Social life and customs; Religion -- Pictorial works; Southern States -- Pictorial works; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Digital inkjet prints; mp3 files; Archive for Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Contents of Collection
- Photographic Prints Series, 1980-1989, (9 boxes)
  Black and white and color photographic prints, with supporting contact and proof prints, of portfolios created by Tom Rankin. Arranged alphabetically by project title: Larry Brown; Mississippi Delta; Portraits of the American South; and Sacred Space.
  - Larry Brown, 1990s, (20 prints)
    - 11x14, b/w, gelatin silver prints, signed
      Portraits of Mississippi writer Larry Brown with his family and friends in Mississippi.
      - Larry Brown on porch swing at Jefferson Ave., Oxford, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Seated outside with jars in foreground, Tula (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Wearing white tee shirt holding Lilly (puppy dog) (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Larry and Mary Annie on grass, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Larry Brown riding and playing guitar (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Larry wearing dark button down shirt standing in front of vines, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Larry and Charlie Jacobs with boat on bank (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Larry at Charlie Jacobs funeral, Bolivar County (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Larry resting on hoe in garden, Oxford (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 13x16, 16x20, digital color and traditional "C" prints, signed
      All locations are in Mississippi.
      - Larry Brown and Richard Howorth from behind, 13x16 digital color print (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Larry Brown and Richard Howorth, 13x16 digital color print (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Blue striped shirt, 16x20 digital color print (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 11x14, b/w, gelatin silver prints, signed
      Unless otherwise specified, all locations are in Mississippi
      - Larry cleaning Shane's deer, Yocana (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Larry with beer and cigarette looking up, Oxford (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Larry burning, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Larry shirtless leaning on fence post, Tula, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Larry and Mary Annie fishing, Tula (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Larry Brown and Johnny Miles smoking, Copiah County (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Larry Brown with rack of horns, Copiah County (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Larry Brown in doorway of shed, Oxford (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Near the Cross: Mississippi Delta, late 1980s-early 1990s, (27 prints)
    Images document and reflect on spiritual and religious practices in the Mississippi Delta region of the Southern United States. Dominant subjects include churches, individuals associated with the churches, cemetery sites, and baptisms.
    - Mt. Tinna M. B. Church, Scott, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Bethlehem No. 2 M. B. Church, Shaw, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Campbellsville Church, Holly Bluff, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Candidate for baptism, fourth week in August, Perthshire, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Baptism, Jerusalem M. B. Church, Mound Bayou, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Candidate for baptism, Mound Bayou, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Handmade gravestones, Mound Bayou, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Mt. Pleasant M. B. Church, Beulah, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Church on Deer Creek, Estill, Mississippi, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Reverend E. B. Brown, Mt. Pleasant M. B. Church, Beulah, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Bethlehem No. 2 M. B. Church, Shaw, 1992 (Box 1)
    - St. James Missionary Baptist Church, Jonestown, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Near Litton, Mississippi, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Abundant Life Church, Lamont, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Brooks Chapel M. B. Church, Greenwood, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Congregation outside Bethlehem No. 2 M. B. Church, Shaw, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Reverend Tom Bronner with neighborhood children, Gunnison, 1989 (Box 1)
    - New Hope Church, Shelby, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Hand-painted window, A. M. E. Church, Indianola, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Grave of Alfred Green, Morning Star Cemetery, Beulah, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Paper Easter flowers, near Tchula, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Near Shaw, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Mt. Olive Church, Bolivar County, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Deacon Fred Davis, Moon Lake, Coahoma County, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Baptism of Cheronda Brown by Reverend Crabtree, Stamps Lake, Perthshire, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Baptism, Moon Lake, Coahoma County, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Prayer after baptism, Moon Lake, Coahoma County, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Sacred Space Series, (65 prints)
    - 11x14, b/w, six gelatin silver prints, signed
      - Rev. Brooks Tobe with dog (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Rev. Bronner in church with his niece (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Three at a time, Moon Lake, Coahoma County (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Baptism, Jerusalem M. B. Church, Mound Bayou, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Deacon Fred Davis, Moon Lake, Coahoma County, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Three young girls being baptized in Moon Lake, Coahoma County, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 8x10, b/w, ten gelatin silver contact prints in 11x14 mats
      - Mt. Olive Church, Bolivar County, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Rev. Tom Bronner with neighborhood children, Gunnison, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Matilda Wray grave, near Shaw, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - New Hope Church, Shelby, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Hand painted window, A. M. E. Church, Indianola, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Mt. Pleasant M. B. Church, Beulah, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Bethlehem No. 2 M. B. Church, Shaw, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Rev. E. B. Brown, Mt. Pleasant M. B. Church, Beulah, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Handmade gravestones, Mound Bayou, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Paper Easter flowers, near Tchula, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 16x20 six vintage "C" prints
      Unless otherwise specified, all locations are in Mississippi.
      - Graves with flowers, Sunflower County (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Church in field, near Litton (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - A stained glass window of three wise men, Indianola (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - (Interior) New Hope Church, Shelby, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - (Exterior) Stained glass windows, Indianola (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Church Street, Indianola (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 16x20, b/w, 13 gelatin silver prints, signed
      - Matilda Wray grave (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - (Exterior) Four hand painted church windows (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Jesus is our Saviours, steeple at Margaret's market, Vicksburg (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - (Interior) Two hand painted church windows (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Propane tank Highway 61 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Evening Star Baptist Church (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Cotton (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Particle board church (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Rev. Tobe on porch (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Mt. Tinna M. B. Church, Scott, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - New Hope Church, Shelby, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - White church, double white doors, electric line cutting through picture, propane tank on side (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - (Interior) Church with dark paneling and carpet (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 16x20, b/w, ten gelatin silver prints, signed
      - Shellmound, Mississippi, 1991 (white frame church with shadow of tree) (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - C.A. Burke Memorial M. B. Church, Rosedale, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Mt. Tinna M.B. Church, near Scott, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Mt. Tinna M.B. Church, near Scott, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Little Ebenezer Baptist Church, Rosedale, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Ida Woodruff grave (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Paper Easter flowers, near Tchula, Mississippi, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Rev. Tom Bronner with neighborhood children, Gunnison, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Rev. E. B. Brown at pulpit, Mt. Pleasant M. B. Church, Beulah, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Graves of Charley Bains and Alfred Green, Beulah (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 16x20, b/w, ten gelatin silver prints in 20x24 mats
      - Grave of Alfred Green, Morning Star Cemetery, Beulah, Mississippi, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Bethlehem No. 2 M. B. Church, Shaw, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Man in striped suspenders standing in doorway. (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Brooks Chapel M. B. Church, Greenwood, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - St. James Missionary Baptist Church, Jonestown, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Abundant Life Church, Lamont, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Campbellsville Church, Holly Bluff, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Near Litton, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Deteriorating church in overgrowth across dirt road from field, puddles in road (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Church on Deer Creek, Estill, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 11x14, b/w, ten gelatin silver prints in 16x20 mats
      - Baptism, Jerusalem M. B. Church, Mound Bayou, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Deacon Fred Davis, Moon Lake, Coahoma County, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Baptism, Moon Lake, Coahoma County, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Candidate for baptism, fourth week in August, Perthshire, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Juandra Griffin and Venita Murray, Moon Lake, Coahoma County, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Prayer after baptism, Moon Lake, Coahoma County, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Congregation outside Bethlehem No. 2 M. B. Church, Shaw, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Baptism of Cheronda Brown by Reverend Crabtree, Stamps Lake, Perthshire, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Baptism, Moon Lake, Coahoma County, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Candidate for baptism, Mound Bayou, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - The American South Series, (25 prints)
    Images were taken in various Southern states, including Alabama, Georgia, Mississippi, and Virginia.
    - 16x20 13 vintage "C" prints
      - Sonny Boy Williamson's grave, Tutwiler, Mississippi (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Barbershop, Columbus, Mississippi (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Dairy Freeze, Crystal Springs, Mississippi (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Oakly and Manuel under wisteria, Sunflower, Mississippi (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Krispy Kreme Christmas window, Atlanta, Georgia (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Rice's Cross Garden, Prattville, Alabama (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - White Castle, Meridian, Mississippi (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Monument, Appomattox, Virginia (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Baseball concession stands, Baker County, Georgia (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - My job work day and night, Mary T. Smith (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Scarecrow, Mary T. Smith (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - (Interior) W. C. Rice's Chapel (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - (vertical) Manuel and wisteria, Sunflower, Mississippi (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 16x20, b/w, three gelatin silver prints, signed
      - (the South) North of Shaw, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Holly Bluff, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - (the South) Margaret's Gro & Mkt, Vicksburg (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 11x14, b/w, 9 gelatin silver prints in 16x20 mats
      - Man in heavy coat next to portable b/w tv (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Man in check shirt and pants smoking cigarette (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Man wearing a dark fedora (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Man standing in front of a highly polished sports car, NC (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Man holding two hounds on a leash (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Man sitting in back of a boat near the motor (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Close-up of a man playing guitar close to his chest (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Man leaning on a fishing boat wearing "CAT" cap (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Man holding a banjo on porch with three cats (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Other Prints Series, (1 print)
    - 11x14, b/w, one silver gelatin print, signed
      - Author Tim McLaurin at home with George, Hillsborough, North Carolina, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Other Materials Series, 2008, (1 mp3 file)
  Digital audio recording of Tom Rankin's talk on February 27, 2008 at the Duke University Libraries exhibit opening of his work, "Near the Cross: Photographs from the Mississippi Delta." This file has been mounted on the library server and is also availalble online through the Duke Libraries digital exhibits website.
  - Tom Rankin exhibit opening talk, 2008 Feb. 27